I'm Sarah Sharp. I'm a deal attorney who
helps people buy and sell businesses
every day. And there are a couple things
you're probably missing in your letter
of intent, especially in my field where
I help people buy and sell accounting
practices. All day long, a lot of
sellers are comparing lots and lots of
letters of intent because there's many
offers out there and it's a super hot
space to buy or sell a business in. When
you are comparing your letters of
intent, it's very easy to focus on the
top line, which is the topline purchase
price. And people will compare, you
know, thinking it's apples to apples,
they'll compare the topline purchase
price from one deal to the next and
decide which one's highest and they go
with that, right? There's so much more
to the purchase price than that top
line. Usually, it's made up of a couple
buckets. If you're in private equity
land, you're probably looking at some
rollover equity, which I will come back
to, but there's a lot of different ways
that you have to value rollover equity.
But even if you're just looking at a
pretty simple buyout, what I see all the
time is really small in one of the
paragraphs of letter intent. It will say
closing cash payment to be reduced by a
normalized working capital amount. What
is that? That can be a really really big
difference especially if you're in a
smaller business like let's say a $3
million business and let's say that you
know you spend several million a year on
your overhead. Well, um, you know,
divide that by 12, multiply that by
three, and that's usually what people
are wanting to get by normalized working
capital. So, that whole closing cash
payment that they're promising is
actually fake number that's going to be
reduced by several hundred,000. And very
common to see that, but it's equally as
common to see somebody who doesn't want
to reduce the purchase price or the
closing cash payment by working capital.
So if you see an offer for $2.5 million
that doesn't want to reduce by working
capital that very much could be the same
as an offer where the top line is 3
million. So that is one big thing to
look at when you're selling and you're
comparing multiple letters of intent.
The other thing is like I mentioned
earlier rollover equity. We are in a
space where there's a lot of people
buying and selling and a lot of private
equity groups uh entering the space. And
with the advent of private equity
groups, all of a sudden people started
to offer rollover equity. In my space
with accountants, there's a pretty
significant distrust of rollover equity.
And that's for good reason because
ultimately rollover equity is kind of
nebulous and it's very hard for
accountants to get their mind around
what it means. Um, if you are comparing
multiple letters of intent, you might
miss that rollover equity isn't the same
in all of them. So even if you value
you're comparing one deal that values
rollover equity $1 and you compare it $1
to $1, there are a lot of differences.
For instance, um how did they come to
that value? Right? Um so if a company is
buying you out private equity group and
they say that the rollover equity is
worth, let's say a million dollars, how
did they determine that? And that's an
okay thing to ask. You can ask that. You
can ask buyers where they got their
money and what kind of approvals they
need to be able to close the deal. You
can ask all kinds of things. So ask how
do you value your rollover equity? But
even if you know they use the exact same
valuation metric um to establish the
rollover equity uh that they're giving
you as part of your purchase price, it
makes a big difference as to what entity
that equity is in. So sometimes people
give you rollover equity in the new
company that they're setting up to house
the assets that you're buying they're
buying of yours as a brand new company
and it might have some value. It might
have significant value. I mean obviously
you're selling it for significant value,
right? So that's something. It's
certainly a good thing. But if you are
comparing that to rollover equity in a
parent company, and a parent company is
a company like at the top of the chain
of the private equity group where maybe
um they have acquired multiple little
entities underneath it and they're
offering rollover equity in the parent
company. That could be of a lot greater
value depending, right? Um but just
because it's scary and intimidating
doesn't mean you shouldn't ask questions
and dig in. It's important that you
understand it and nobody like is born
knowing anything about rollover equity.
So ask a lot of questions. Um I have had
probably every single seller say I would
so much rather have a seller promisory
note than um a grant of rollover equity.
And the the buyers can't believe that
because it's this phenomenal opportunity
to be on the ground floor of a really
cool investment. One of the reasons that
I think sellers should seriously
consider offers that have rollover
equity is because uh at the end of the
day when you get several million dollar
when you're closing your deal, you're
going to have to turn around and figure
out what to invest that in. And if
you're like a lot of us, you know,
you've you've got a lot of money in the
stock market. You don't really need more
of that. Real estate, you know, is down
and not really probably what you're
looking to spend your retirement doing.
And so what are you going to invest in?
you have this great opportunity to
invest in a this kind of closely held
company that um is something you really
really really intimately understand and
can monitor. I very rarely see a rollup
which means people buying lots of little
uh accounting practices um not sell for
a profit cuz what they're doing is
they're taking you know something that
trades at a certain lower IBIDA because
it's small they're adding a bunch of
them together and they're selling them
at the higher IBIDA that a bigger
company warrants. That's a no-brainer.
So, you know, roll over equity can be
really, really, really valuable. But it
depends. Another thing to consider when
you're comparing one letter of intent to
the next is where are you in the life
cycle of that? Because if you are
getting a rollover equity that's worth
$1 per share the minute before they do
that big liquidation event where they
sell, then you're not going to get that
much upside, right? I mean, you're going
to get your money. You're going to get a
dollar per share probably with a lot of
restrictions related to like rolling
over into the new company and things
like that. Um, so not as good as if you
are more on the ground floor of a
company where all of a sudden you've got
the ability to get that $1 a share and
see them acquire 20 more practices and
sell for way way way higher than a
dollar per share. But any new company
also comes with more risk. So how do you
compare those to each other? And for
these reasons, a lot of people kind of
overlook rollover equity and pretend
like it's nothing, which I think is a
mistake. So, do not when you're
comparing one letter of intent to the
next, do not overlook rollover equity,
don't sleep on it. It's a phenomenal
opportunity. Perhaps even consider
choosing a buyer that has best rollover
equity upside for you because you will
absolutely have the ability to turn that
$2 million of rollover equity into 7
million of rollover equity. And that is
the the thing they call the second bite
of the apple. And it's pretty magical.
So, you know, if you're considering
selling, there's a lot more to meet the
eye than in your LOIS than just the
topline purchase price. It really
matters what they're made of. I'm Sarah
Sharp. I'm a deal attorney who helps
people buy and sell businesses every
day. If you found this valuable, please
like, subscribe, go check out
dealacademy.org where I have courses
that talk about buying and selling
businesses primarily accounting
practices.